<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R4/fhir-single.xsd">
  <a name="background"> </a>
  <h3>Adaptive Questionnaire Background</h3>
  <p>
    Adaptive Forms follow an architecture where a questionnaire is not pre-defined, rather the questionnaire is dynamically developed based on
    previous answers to questions chosen from an item bank of questions.  This type of administration is also known as Computerized Adaptive Testing (CAT),
    or administration of Adaptive Questionnaires. In these cases, a set of questions (typically 4 to 12) are administered from a question bank containing
    numerous questions.  The selected questions are based on Item Response Theory (IRT) algorithms which look at the answers provided and select the
    next question based on IRT algorithms.  The questions are selected to quickly obtain the necessary outcomes (e.g. assessing a person's physical
    function) using fewer questions rather than administering a large question bank.  These small sets of questions still provide the necessary confidence and
    scores required to interpret the data appropriately as if the whole questionnaire was administered. he adaptive process relies on the 
    <a href="OperationDefinition-Questionnaire-next-question.html">$next-question</a> operation to dynamically determine and retrieve 
    subsequent questions based on previous answers.
  </p>
  <a name="model"> </a>
  <h3>Adaptive Questionnaire Administration Abstract Model and Actors</h3>
  <table class="grid">
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <th>Profiles:</th>
        <td>
          <ul>
            <li><a href="StructureDefinition-sdc-questionnaire-adapt.html">Adaptive Questionnaire Profile</a></li>
            <li><a href="StructureDefinition-sdc-questionnaireresponse-adapt.html">Adaptive QuestionnaireResponse Profile</a></li>
            <li><a href="StructureDefinition-sdc-questionnaire-adapt-srch.html">Adaptive Questionnaire Search Profile</a></li>
          </ul>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Relevant Extensions:</th>
        <td>
          <ul>
            <li><a href="StructureDefinition-sdc-questionnaire-questionnaireAdaptive.html">questionnaireAdaptive</a></li>
          </ul>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>Example Questionnaires:</th>
        <td>
          <ul>
            <li><a href="QuestionnaireResponse-adaptive-questionnaireresponse-sdc-example-phq9-start.html">Adaptive PHQ9 - Start</a></li>
            <li><a href="QuestionnaireResponse-adaptive-questionnaireresponse-sdc-example-phq9.html">Adaptive PHQ9 - Complete</a></li>
          </ul>
        </td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
  <p>
    The section explains the process of administering an Adaptive Questionnaire and the actors (systems) involved.  Figure 1 below shows the abstract model of
    the administration process.
  </p>
  <a name="fig1"> </a>
  <img src="adaptive-questionnaire-model.png" alt="Adaptive Questionnaire Administration Abstract Model"/>
  <p>
    <b>Figure 1: Adaptive Questionnaire Administration Abstract Model</b>
  </p>
  <a name="dataflow"> </a>
  <h4>Actors, Definitions and Data Flow</h4>
  <p>
    <b>External Assessment Center:</b> The External IRT based Assessment Center is a system that can administer a questionnaire based on
    IRT algorithms.  The data that is necessary for the administration is only the initial item bank.  The External Assessment Center does not need to
    know about the specific patient identity or any other clinical information.  The Assessment Center will use algorithms recommended by the
    Questionnaire designer to determine how to administer the questionnaire.
  </p>
  <p>
    <b>Patient Facing Administration App:</b> The Patient Facing Administration App is the actual app that is being used to present the questions to
    the patient.  It can be an EHR, a SMART on FHIR App, an Independent PRO Administration App.
  </p>
  <a name="flow"> </a>
  <h3>Data Flow Description for Adaptive Questionnaires Administration</h3>
  <p>
    As shown in Figure 1 above, the Patient Facing Administration App (EHR, Care Delivery System, Independent App or SMART on FHIR App) acts as the client
    and initiates the administration process.
  </p>
  <p>
    The following section describes the steps that take place when completing an adaptive Questionnaire and also provides examples of the content sent to and received back from the <a href="OperationDefinition-Questionnaire-next-question.html">next question</a> operation. With regard to the server's response, it is possible that more than one new question is returned in the questionnaire, and previously sent questions that were unanswered might not be sent back by the server.
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <b>Step 0:</b> <p> Before initiating the administration process for an adaptive questionnaire, the app must first locate the appropriate
       questionnaire. This can be done through various mechanisms such as performing a search operation, referencing a Task resource, 
       or other mechanism. The questionnaire being located <code>SHALL</code> conform to the <code>Adaptive Questionnaire Search Profile</code>, which 
       ensures that it is discoverable and compliant with adaptive questionnaire requirements.
       </p>
       <p> Additionally, the located questionnaire <code>SHALL</code> include the <code>questionnaireAdaptive</code> extension. This extension explicitly indicates 
       that the questionnaire supports adaptiveness and may provide details about the endpoints where the $next-question operation can 
       be invoked. If the questionnaireAdaptive extension doesn't specify a URL, the location must be independently negotiated, though as a fallback, 
       try the server on which the Questionnaire is hosted. This step ensures that the app knows whether the questionnaire is adaptive and where to send subsequent 
       requests for the adaptive process.
       </p>
    </li>  
    <li>
      <b>Step 1:</b> The available adaptive questionnaires are loaded into the Assessment Center.
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <b>Step 2:</b> The administration is initiated with a specific Adaptive Questionnaire.
      </p>
      <p>
        <b>
          <i>Request</i>
        </b>
      </p>
      <p>
        <code>POST [base]/Questionnaire/$next-question</code>
      </p>
      <p>
        <b>Request Body</b>
      </p>
      <div class="tabs">
        <div class="tab">
          <input type="radio" id="code-prop-json" name="req1-group"/>
          <label for="req1-json">JSON</label>
          <div class="content-in-tab">{% fragment QuestionnaireResponse/adaptive-questionnaireresponse-sdc-example-phq9-start JSON EXCEPT:contained.ofType(Questionnaire)|questionnaire|status EXCEPT:id|derivedFrom BASE:contained %}</div>
        </div>
        <div class="tab">
          <input type="radio" id="code-prop-xml" name="req1-group"/>
          <label for="req1-xml">XML</label>
          <div class="content-in-tab">{% fragment QuestionnaireResponse/adaptive-questionnaireresponse-sdc-example-phq9-start XML EXCEPT:contained.ofType(Questionnaire)|questionnaire|status EXCEPT:id|derivedFrom BASE:contained %}</div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <p>
        NOTE: No items in QuestionnaireResponse or Questionnaire because process is just starting.  (It's possible in some cases to have a pre-populated adaptive QuestionnaireResponse that includes initial items in both the Questionnaire and QuestionnaireResponse, but we're keeping the example simple/typical.)
      </p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <b>Step 3:</b> The Assessment Center responds to the start request with a Questionnaire and the first item for administration.
      </p>
      <p>
        <b>Response Body</b>
      </p>
      <div class="tabs">
        <div class="tab">
          <input type="radio" id="code-prop-json" name="resp1-group"/>
          <label for="resp1-json">JSON</label>
          <div class="content-in-tab">{% fragment QuestionnaireResponse/adaptive-questionnaireresponse-sdc-example-phq9-start JSON EXCEPT:contained.ofType(Questionnaire)|questionnaire|status EXCEPT:id|derivedFrom|item BASE:contained EXCEPT:item[0] BASE:contained.item %}</div>
        </div>
        <div class="tab">
          <input type="radio" id="code-prop-xml" name="resp1-group"/>
          <label for="resp1-xml">XML</label>
          <div class="content-in-tab">{% fragment QuestionnaireResponse/adaptive-questionnaireresponse-sdc-example-phq9-start XML EXCEPT:contained.ofType(Questionnaire)|questionnaire|status EXCEPT:id|derivedFrom|item BASE:contained EXCEPT:item[0] BASE:contained.item %}</div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </li>
    <li>
      <b>Step 4:</b> The Patient Facing Administration App will then display the question to the user and collect the response.
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <b>Step 5:</b> The Patient Facing Administration App will then send the answer to the Assessment Center and ask for the next question.
        The Assessment Center will use the answer to determine the next question based on the algorithm and respond back with the next question until the assessment is done.
      </p>
      <p>
        <b>Request Body</b>
      </p>
      <div class="tabs">
        <div class="tab">
          <input type="radio" id="code-prop-json" name="req2-group"/>
          <label for="req2-json">JSON</label>
          <div class="content-in-tab">{% fragment QuestionnaireResponse/adaptive-questionnaireresponse-sdc-example-phq9-start JSON EXCEPT:contained.ofType(Questionnaire)|questionnaire|status EXCEPT:id|derivedFrom|item BASE:contained EXCEPT:item[0] BASE:contained.item EXCEPT:item[0] BASE:item %}</div>
        </div>
        <div class="tab">
          <input type="radio" id="code-prop-xml" name="req2-group"/>
          <label for="req2-xml">XML</label>
          <div class="content-in-tab">{% fragment QuestionnaireResponse/adaptive-questionnaireresponse-sdc-example-phq9-start XML EXCEPT:contained.ofType(Questionnaire)|questionnaire|status EXCEPT:id|derivedFrom|item BASE:contained EXCEPT:item[0] BASE:contained.item EXCEPT:item[0] BASE:item %}</div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <p>
        <b>Response Body</b>
      </p>
      <div class="tabs">
        <div class="tab">
          <input type="radio" id="code-prop-json" name="resp2-group"/>
          <label for="resp2-json">JSON</label>
          <div class="content-in-tab">{% fragment QuestionnaireResponse/adaptive-questionnaireresponse-sdc-example-phq9-start JSON EXCEPT:contained.ofType(Questionnaire)|questionnaire|status EXCEPT:id|derivedFrom|item BASE:contained EXCEPT:item[0]|item[1] BASE:contained.item EXCEPT:item[0] BASE:item %}</div>
        </div>
        <div class="tab">
          <input type="radio" id="code-prop-xml" name="resp2-group"/>
          <label for="resp2-xml">XML</label>
          <div class="content-in-tab">{% fragment QuestionnaireResponse/adaptive-questionnaireresponse-sdc-example-phq9-start XML EXCEPT:contained.ofType(Questionnaire)|questionnaire|status EXCEPT:id|derivedFrom|item BASE:contained EXCEPT:item[0]|item[1] BASE:contained.item EXCEPT:item[0] BASE:item %}</div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </li>
    <li>
      <b>Step 4 is repeated as long as new questions are received and the status is "in-progress"</b>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <b>Step 6:</b> If the Assessment Center determines that the assessment is done, it will respond with the final results which will contain all
          the questions that were answered, along with the answers, the individual scores and the overall score.
      </p>
      <p>
        <b>Request Body</b>
      </p>
      <div class="tabs">
        <div class="tab">
          <input type="radio" id="code-prop-json" name="req3-group"/>
          <label for="req3-json">JSON</label>
          <div class="content-in-tab">{% fragment QuestionnaireResponse/adaptive-questionnaireresponse-sdc-example-phq9-start JSON EXCEPT:contained.ofType(Questionnaire)|questionnaire|status EXCEPT:id|derivedFrom|item BASE:contained EXCEPT:item.last() BASE:contained.item EXCEPT:item.last() BASE:item %}</div>
        </div>
        <div class="tab">
          <input type="radio" id="code-prop-xml" name="req3-group"/>
          <label for="req3-xml">XML</label>
          <div class="content-in-tab">{% fragment QuestionnaireResponse/adaptive-questionnaireresponse-sdc-example-phq9-start XML EXCEPT:contained.ofType(Questionnaire)|questionnaire|status EXCEPT:id|derivedFrom|item BASE:contained EXCEPT:item.last() BASE:contained.item EXCEPT:item.last() BASE:item %}</div>
        </div>
      </div>      
      <p>
        <b>Response Body with Completed Status indicating completion of Administration</b>
      </p>
      <div class="tabs">
        <div class="tab">
          <input type="radio" id="code-prop-json" name="resp3-group"/>
          <label for="resp3-json">JSON</label>
          <div class="content-in-tab">{% fragment QuestionnaireResponse/adaptive-questionnaireresponse-sdc-example-phq9 JSON EXCEPT:contained.ofType(Questionnaire)|questionnaire|status EXCEPT:id|derivedFrom|item BASE:contained EXCEPT:item.last() BASE:contained.item EXCEPT:item.last() BASE:item %}</div>
        </div>
        <div class="tab">
          <input type="radio" id="code-prop-xml" name="resp3-group"/>
          <label for="resp3-xml">XML</label>
          <div class="content-in-tab">{% fragment QuestionnaireResponse/adaptive-questionnaireresponse-sdc-example-phq9 XML EXCEPT:contained.ofType(Questionnaire)|questionnaire|status EXCEPT:id|derivedFrom|item BASE:contained EXCEPT:item.last() BASE:contained.item EXCEPT:item.last() BASE:item %}</div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </li>
  </ul>
  <a name="adaptive-population"> </a>
  <h3>Adaptive Population</h3>
    <p>
      Adaptive questionnaires can support population under certain constraints. The following guidance applies when using population mechanisms with adaptive forms:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>Can use observation-based or expression-based, but not StructureMap.</li>
      <li>Systems should cache previously populated variable values between calls to <code>$next-question</code>.</li>
      <li>New variables and even libraries may appear in subsequent iterations of the Questionnaire and clients will need to look for these.</li>
    </ul>
  <a name="security"> </a>
  <h3>Security Considerations</h3>
  <p>
    Because the adaptive process involves sending answers to a separate endpoint in order to determine the "next question", the connection should be appropriately 
    protected based on the type of information that might be exchanged.  (And given that there is no way to be completely certain what questions will be asked, it 
    is best to err on the side of safety and presume that sensitive information might be shared.)  As well, there should be trust between the Form Filler and the 
    nextQuestion endpoint as the server performing the operation will obviously have access to that information.  In general, servers performing the nextQuestion 
    operation SHOULD NOT take any action with the data other than to return the response and potentially log the information.  "Submission" of a completed form should 
    always be a distinct action taken by the client.
  </p>
</div>
