<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R4/fhir-single.xsd">
  <p>
    This section covers overarching guidance around the use of Questionnaires and QuestionnaireResponses that does not cleanly fit into any of the other pages.
  </p>
  <a name="noanswer"> </a>
  <h3>Handling QuestionnaireResponse items without answers</h3>
  <p>
    When an answer is not present for a question or a set of questions in a group, there are two legal ways to represent this in a completed QuestionnaireResponse:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Keep the item (with its item text), but do not include answers</li>
    <li>Strip the item out of the QuestionnaireResponse entirely</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    (Note that when performing <a href="populate.html">population</a>, the recommendation is to not strip out disabled items until such time as the form is marked as completed.)
  </p>
  <p>
    The first approach allows rendering the full response (including unanswered questions) without access to the Questionnaire.  Stripping unanswered items means that rendering 
    unanswered questions requires access to the Questionnaire, which might not always be possible for downstream systems.  As well, there may be extensions on the item that 
    convey useful information (e.g. whether the user saw the item, removed populated answers, etc.) even if no answer is present.  Form fillers <b>SHOULD NOT</b> remove items without 
    answers if there are extensions present unless it is known they are not relevant.
  </p>
  <p>
    The second approach can save a considerable amount of storage space, especially for forms that are often sparsely populated.
  </p>
  <p>
    Systems <b>SHALL</b> safely handle QuestionnaireResponses that use either approach and <b>SHALL NOT</b> ascribe distinct meaning to an item being omitted vs. being present with no answer.
  </p>

  <div class="new-content">
    <a name="assessing"> </a>
    <h3>Assessing QuestionnaireResponses</h3>
    <p>
    In some cases, knowing that a QuestionnaireResponse is 'valid' against a particular Questionnaire is not sufficient.  Instead, there is a need to evaluate that answers
    provided against a set of criteria - to diagnose, evaluate risk, assess competence, or some similar purpose.  There are a number of mechanisms that support such evaluation,
    as well as special considerations around questionnaire design when doing so.
    </p>
    
    <a name="assessmech"> </a>
    <h4>Assessment mechanisms</h4>
    <p>
    The most common mechanism of evaluation is by 'scoring' particular answers.  Different answers to a question are associated with differing weights.  By performing a
    mathmatical operation on the weights of the answers (typically simple summation), an overall score can be determined and the desired evaluation can be performed based
    on the score value.  This is done using two extensions:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="{{site.data.fhir.ver.ext}}/StructureDefinition-itemWeight.html">itemWeight</a> allows assigining a weight to answers</li>
      <li><a href="{{site.data.fhir.ver.ext}}/StructureDefinition-sdc-questionnaire-calculatedExpression.html">sdc-questionnaire-calculatedExpression</a> allows dynamically 
        calculating a value based on the answers to questions (including an easy way to reference weights using the FHIRPath 
        <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}fhirpath.html#fn-weight">weight()</a> function).</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
    A second mechanism is to use <a href="extraction.html">extraction</a> mechanism to either complete a second QuestionnaireResponse with assessment results of the
    first form, or a <a href="populate.html">population</a> mechanism to define a second form that grabs information from the originally completed QuestionnaireResponse.
    Extraction can also be used (with either complex FHIRPath or CQL) to extract a score directly into an Observation.
    </p>
    <p>
    The third mechanism is to leverage a second <a href="StructureDefinition-sdc-questionnaire-answerKey.html">answerKey</a> QuestionnaireResponse that identifies the
    'correct' or 'preferred' responses.  A human or computer software can then evaluate the completed QuestionnaireResponse against the answerKey, producing an
    evaluation.  Evaluation comments can also be embedded in the completed QuestionnaireResponse using the 
    <a href="StructureDefinition-sdc-questionnaire-item-answerAssessment">sdc-questionnaire-item-answerAssessment.html</a> extension.  Examples are provided of both
    a <a href="QuestionnaireResponse-trivia-response-answer-key.html">key</a>, as well as a <a href="QuestionnaireResponse-trivia-response.html">QuestionnaireResponse</a> 
    evaluated against that key.
    </p>
    
    <a name="concealing"> </a>
    <h4>Concealing assessments</h4>
    <p>
    In some cases, it can be problematic if the individual completing the Questionnaire is aware of the score as it can change how they complete the form.  (For example,
    if completing a test, it would not be helpful if the user knew how well they had done and had the ability to adjust their answers.)
    </p>
    <p>
    If the concern is concealing the weights and calculations while the user is completing the form, but no concern that the user will have access to the underlying
    Questionnaire definition, there are a couple of options.  Which of the two is appropriate depends on whether it is appropriate or necessary for the user to see the 
    score at some point.
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>The data element that calculates the score can either be <a href="{{site.data.fhir.ver.ext}}/StructureDefinition-questionnaire-hidden.html">hidden</a>.  The
        score will be present in the exchanged QuestionnaireResponse, but never visible to end-users.</li>
      <li>Alternatively, the element can be flagged as only visible during a <a href="{{site.data.fhir.ver.ext}}/StructureDefinition-questionnaire-usageMode.html">usageMode</a> 
        of <code>display</code>, such that the answer is only visible once the QuestionnaireResponse is marked as complete.  In this case, however, there would need to be a 
        mechanism that prevents the user from going back into edit mode once the completed form is visible.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
    If there is a concern about users (or others) having access to the Questionnaire definition itself, then embedding the scores, calculations, or extraction rules in the 
    Questionnaire completed by the end user is an issue.  In this case, the mechanism for concealment needs to separate the 'assessment' metadata into a separate mechanism.
    The 'population' approach discussed above provides one mechanism, as the logic lives in the definition of the 'target' instrument rather than the source.  Another
    option is to use <a href="derive.html">derived Questionnaires</a>.  A secondary Questionnaire that mirrors the first in terms of hierarchy, linkIds, data types, permitted
    answers, etc. is created that inserts the additional calculation metadata.  That could include weights, extraction logic, or additional items to hold calculated scores.
    The original Questionnaire is distributed to systems for completion, while the derived Questionnaire is closely held and is used with the resulting QuestionnaireResponses
    to support assessment.
    </p>
  </div>  
</div>
