<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R4/fhir-single.xsd">
  <a name="algorithm"> </a>
  <h3>Algorithm</h3>
  <p>
    The assembly process for a modular questionnaire proceeds as follows:
  </p>
  <ol>
    <li>
      Resolve all <a href="StructureDefinition-sdc-questionnaire-subQuestionnaire.html">subQuestionnaire</a> extensions as described in the 
      <a href="modular.html#modular">Modular Forms</a> page.  If there is an issue resolving any of the subQuestionnaires or applying the reolution
      process results in any errors, the operation <b>SHOULD</b> fail.
    </li>
    <li>
      Propagate all relevant information from any declared <code>item.definition</code> elements on all resulting items, as described on the
      <a href="modular.html#element">Modular Forms</a> page.
    </li>
    <li>
      Remove the <a href="StructureDefinition-sdc-questionnaire-is-modular.html">is-modular</a> extension from the Questionnaire - because it 
      is not modular anymore!
    </li>
    <li>
      Add the <a href="SearchParameter-questionnaire-assembledFrom.html"></a> extension, pointing to the canonical URL and version of the 
      Questionnaire that was assembled.
    </li>
    <li>
      Modify the Questionnaire.version to either be a UUID or append "-assembled".
    </li>
    <li>
      Optionally, check the resulting Questionnaire to ensure that it is valid according to the base Questionnaire and possibly any declared 
      profiles.  If the resulting Questionnaire is not valid, return a warning.
    </li>
  </ol>
  <p>
    The result of the operation will be one of three things:
  </p>
	<ul>
		<li>
      If there are any errors, there will be a 4xx or 5xx error code and, ideally an 
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}operationoutcome.html">OperationOutcome</a> as the body of the response.
    </li>
    <li>
      If there are no errors, warnings or information messages that result from the assembly process, the body can just be the bare Questionnaire
      resource that resulted from the operation.
    </li>
    <li>
      If there are any warnings or information messages, then the body will be a <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}parameters.html">Parameters</a>
      instance with two parameters - 'response' containing the reulting Questionnaire and 'outcome' containing an OperationOutcome with the warning
      and/or information messages.
    </li>
	</ul>
	<a name="examples"> </a>
	<h3>Examples</h3>
	<p>
    An example of a modular Questionnaire (as a sample input to the operation) can be found <a href="Questionnaire-sdc-modular-root.html">here</a>.
  </p>
	<p>
    An example of the result of invoking a modular Questionnaire (as a sample output from the operation) can be found 
    <a href="Parameters-sdc-modular-root-assembled.html">here</a>.
  </p>
</div>
