<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R4/fhir-single.xsd">
	<a name="project"> </a>
	<h3>Project</h3>
	<p>
    The original version of this implementation guide was prepared as a U.S. Realm Specification on behalf of the Structured Data Capture project - an
    effort under the <a href="http://www.healthit.gov/newsroom/about-onc">U.S. Office of the National Coordinator (ONC)</a>'s Standards and Infrastructure
    (S &amp; I) Framework.
  </p>
  <p>
    The new version of this guide was developed by the <a href="http://www.hl7.org/Special/committees/fiwg">FHIR Infrastructure work group</a> in collaboration with and thanks to funding from the
    <a href="https://lhncbc.nlm.nih.gov/">Lister Hill National Center for Biomedical Communications</a> of the <a href="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/">U.S.
    National Library of Medicine (NLM)</a>.  As part of the revision of the implementation guide, the very limited portions of the implementation guide that
    were U.S. specific have been relaxed, making the guide applicable to all countries.  Representatives from several non-U.S. jurisdictions were part of the 
    project calls where the revisions to the implementation guide were determined.
  </p>
  <p>
    Readers of this IG should be aware that there is a distinct (and non-FHIR-based) implementation guide developed and maintained by IHE that also goes
    by the name of "SDC - Structured Data Capture".  More information about the IHE initiative can be found 
    <a href="https://wiki.ihe.net/index.php/Structured_Data_Capture">here</a>.  While there are similar workflows envisioned and the two projects originated
    as part of the same initiative, the two approaches are not compatible or easily mappable - in part because of FHIR's decision to split Questionnaire and QuestionnaireResponse
    into distinct resources, while the IHE specification uses a single structure for both.  Implementers instructed to "comply with SDC" should confirm <i>which</i> 
    'SDC' specification they're expected to comply with...
  </p>
  <p>
    Ongoing maintenance of the SDC IG, as well as providing support on the use of the FHIR Questionnaire resources in general is managed through the
    FHIR Infrastructure work group's SDC project.  This group holds weekly calls and conducts regular connectathons and also monitors the
    <a href="https://chat.fhir.org/#narrow/stream/179255-questionnaire">Questionnaire stream</a> on http://chat.fhir.org.  It also reviews feedback provided 
    about the specification submitted by those using the 'propose a change' link at the bottom of this and all other IG pages.  Project details, minutes and 
    call information can be found on the
    <a href="https://confluence.hl7.org/display/FHIRI/FHIR+Structured+Data+Capture">project Confluence page</a>.  Additional participants are welcome to
    join as we further refine the implementation guide and work to increase adoption through connectathons, open-source projects and other mechanisms.
  </p>
	<a name="credits"> </a>
	<h3>Credits</h3>
	<p>
    This implementation guide represents thousands of person-hours of discussion, development work, and testing.  The following are some of the key
    participants in the work, but many more have assisted through connectathons testing, asking questions and participating in conference calls.
	</p>
	<table>
    <tbody>
      <tr style="color:blue">
        <th>Role</th>
        <th>Contributor(s)</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><i>Lead author:</i></td>
        <td>
          <b>Lloyd McKenzie</b> (Gevity Consulting)
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><i>Additional authors:</i></td>
        <td>
          <b>Russ Buchanan</b> (Gevity Consulting)<br/>
          <b>Sheridan Cook</b> (Gevity Consulting)<br/>
          <b>Raman Dhanoa</b> (Gevity Consulting)<br/>
          <b>Joee Garcia</b> (Gevity Consulting)
          <b>Brian Postlethwaite</b> (Microsoft Research)<br/>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><i>Key contributors:</i></td>
        <td>
          <b>Liz Amos</b> (U.S. National Library of Medicine - NLM)<br/>
          <b>Ilya Beda</b> (Beda Software)<br/>
          <b>Nagesh Bashyam</b> (Drajer)<br/>
          <b>Oliver Egger</b> (Agile Health Information Systems AHDIS)<br/>
          <b>Alex Goel</b> (College of American Pathologists - CAP)<br/>
          <b>Grahame Grieve</b> (Health Intersections)<br/>
          <b>Eric Haas</b> (Health eData)<br/>
          <b>David Hay</b> (HealthcareInterop)<br/>
          <b>Stoyan Halkaliev</b> (NursIT Institute)<br/>
          <b>Ana Kostadinovska</b> (Philips Healthcare)<br/>
          <b>David Kwan</b> (Cancer Care Ontario - CCO)<br/>
          <b>Don Langlois</b> (B.C. Provincial Health Services Agency - PHSA)<br/>
          <b>Paul Lynch</b> (U.S. National Library of Medicine - NLM)<br/>
          <b>Clem McDonald</b> (U.S. National Library of Medicine - NLM)<br/>
          <b>Peter Muir</b> (PJM Consulting)<br/>
          <b>Joe Quinn</b> (Medecision)<br/>
          <b>Robinette Renner</b> (U.S. National Marrow Donor Program - NMDP)<br/>
          <b>Brenin Rhodes</b> (Smile Digital Health)<br/>
          <b>Bryn Rhodes</b> (Alphora/Smile Digital Health)<br/>
          <b>Maria Ryzhikova</b> (Health Samurai)<br/>
          <b>Jose Costa Tiexiera</b> (HL7 Belgium)<br/>
          <b>Olga Vovk</b> (General Dynamics Information Technology - GDIT)<br/>
          <b>Yunwei Wang</b> (MITRE)
          <b>Ye Wang</b> (U.S. National Library of Medicine - NLM)
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td><i>Initial Release Key contributors:</i></td>
        <td>
          <b>Clem McDonald</b> (U.S. National Library of Medicine - NLM)<br/>
          <b>Mark Roche</b> (Roche Consulting)<br/>
          <b>Vijay Shaw</b> (JBS International)<br/>
          <b>Richard Moldwin</b> (College of American Pathologists - CAP)<br/>
          <b>Denise Warzel</b> (U.S. National Cancer Institute - NCI)
        </td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
  <p>
    This list inevitably fails to mention many of the individuals who contributed their time and
    energy to developing this specification and making it better.  Thanks to all of you!
  </p>  
</div>
