<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R4/fhir-single.xsd">
  <a name="modes"> </a>
  <h3>Display Modes</h3>
  <p>
    Most of the focus in SDC around the 'display' of QuestionnaireResponses is during the form completion stage.  This is the phase when questions, display,
    and other items are presented to a user for the purpose of collecting information.  <a href="populate.html">Population</a> happens either prior to or 
    during this phase, all of the <a href="behavior.html">Form Behavior</a> functionality occurs during this phase, and the vast majority of the 
    <a href="rendering.html">Form Rendering</a> structures are also used during this process.
  </p>
  <p>
    However, there is a second phase to the QuestionnaireResponse's lifespan that also involves rendering - displaying a completed form to an end user to
    allow the captured data to be visually consumed.  This representation serves a different purpose.  It is no longer trying to <i>capture</i> data in an
    efficient manner.  Instead, it is trying to allow users to <i>consume</i> information in an efficient manner.  For this reason, the rendering requirements
    may differ.
  </p>
  <p>
    In SDC, these two different focuses are referred to as 'usage modes' - `capture` and `display`.
  </p>
  
  <a name="rendering"> </a>
  <h3>Display rendering approaches</h3>
  <p>
    There are four approaches to rendering completed forms defined by SDC: Default, Answers only, Item-controlled, and Custom-Liquid.  These approaches and
    their pros and cons are described below.
  </p>
  
  <a name="default"> </a>
  <h4>Default Display</h4>
  <p>
    The default approach to rendering a completed form is to display it in exactly the same manner as is used for data capture:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>All groups, display items, and questions are rendered</li>
    <li>Answers appear within the associated entry control structure (selected radio buttons or check boxes, selected items within drop-downs, filled in 
      text-boxes, etc.</li>
    <li>Where multiple answer choices were available, all permitted choices are exposed, with those that were and were not selected being made visually evident
      as appropriate based on the control type used.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    Depending on the tool performing the rendering, the controls allowing data capture might or might not be 'locked' as read-only
  </p>
  <p>
    The benefit of this display mode is that a Form Filler does not need to support more than one rendering approach.  It renders completed forms and in-progress
    questionnaires exactly the same way.  Also, if the reader of the QuestionnaireResponse is not familiar with the design of the Questionnaire, they may be
    interested in knowing what answer choices were available but not selected and what questions were availble but not answered.
  </p>
  <p>
    However, this approach is quite verbose.  Displaying user instructions, non-selected answers, and non-answered questions may mean a great deal of scrolling
    will be necessary to read all answers.  This approach can also create confusion about whether the user is in a mode of "form review" or "form data entry",
    and there's the possibility the user will unintentionally change data as part of the review process.  Finally, this approach doesn't support any customization
    of the display to optimize it for data consumption, such as displaying different items on data review than were visible on data capture, or displaying
    content with different formatting, text, or order.
  </p>
  
  <a name="answeronly"> </a>
  <h4>Answers Only</h4>
  <p>
    In this approach the display of the completed form is more limited.  Questions continue to be displayed in order, however only answers provided by the user
    are visible.  Answer choices not selected by the user are not included and questions not answered are omitted.  Display items are also omitted.  Answers are
    usually rendered as text strings rather than as item controls such as checkboxes or drop-downs.
  </p>
  <p>
    This approach is considerably more concise and allows readers to consume all entered information in a more efficient manner.  However, as a middle ground, it
    suffers from two sets of issues.  For users who aren't familiar with the Questionnaire design and find the decision to not answer questions or not select
    particular choices to be as informative as seeing what the user <i>did</i> select, this approach does not display sufficient information.  And for users who
    want a display that is more optimized for consumption, this approach can still result in a presentation that is more verbose and less optimized than other
    rendering modes.  This approach doesn't allow customizing which items are displayed, the item text, item order, or other rendering.
  </p>
  
  <a name="itemcontrol"> </a>
  <h4>Item controlled</h4>
  <p>
    This approach leverages the <a href="{{site.data.fhir.ver.ext}}/StructureDefinition-questionnaire-usageMode.html">usageMode extension</a>.
    This allows a Questionnaire designer to designate whether items should be visible when capturing data, when displaying a completed form, or both.  With this
    approach, it is possible to have display items that govern data capture only appear when performing data capture, but not display when a user is reviewing a
    completed form.  On the other hand, display items that explain how to interpret a completed form might only display when in 'review' mode.  The same can be
    done with question items, or even whole sections.  A score calculated based on a set of answers might not be displayed during user-entry to prevent influencing
    the user's choices, however it could be made available once the form is  complete.  Calculated answers migh allow determining a 'summary' of certain answers
    for more efficient rendering, while the fine-grained questions covered by the summary might be suppressed.
  </p>
  <p>
    This approach provides more control over the appearance of items, and with calculated values, can produce relatively compact presentations which may even
    change the order of the elements or even display assertions dealing with un-answered questions.  However, there are still limitations to the compactness
    of the view as information will still be presented as questions, answers, and display items 'in order'.  If there is a desire for custom control of formatting,
    such as the use of tables or lists that does not rely on attempting to stitch together HTML tags using FHIRPath or CQL expressions, this mechanism may not
    be sufficiently powerful.  Also, this approach means that additional items must be defined in the Questionnaire to handle the custom display.  Any additional
    questions or groups will be included in the QuestionnaireResponse.  This may not be dsirable if building off a 'standard' Questionnaire with the intention that
    the resulting QuestionnaireResponses will remain valid against the original base Questionnaire.
  </p>
  
  <a name="liquid"> </a>
  <h4>Liquid Rendering</h4>
  <p>
    HL7 defines a generic <!-- TODO - move this to extension pack --><a href="StructureDefinition-instance-narrative-liquid.html">instance-narrative-liquid extension</a> that
    can be used on 'definitional' artifacts (e.g. Questionnaires, PlanDefinitions, Measures, etc.) that allows conveying a computable syntax that defines how
    the narrative of instances of those definitions should appear.  The language used is a special 
    <a href="https://confluence.hl7.org/spaces/FHIR/pages/66938964/FHIR+Liquid+Profile">FHIRPath-aware form of Liquid</a>.
  </p>
  <p>
    The base <a href="https://shopify.github.io/liquid">Liquid language</a> is open source and was developed by Shopify as a simple mechanism to help construct 
    static websites.  The FHIRPath-enabled syntax has slight variations that allow embedding FHIRPath expressions as part of the value content, assignments, and
    conditional and looping expressions.  The combination of FHIRPath and Liquid allows the definition of HTML form renderings as complex as necessary.  Examples
    of potential functionality include:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Embedding complex rendering structures such as lists, tables, hyperlinks, etc.</li>
    <li>Overriding the text and/or formatting of item text and answer values</li>
    <li>Including conditional logic around what content to expose in what circumstances</li>
    <li>Adjusting the order in which content appears</li>
    <li>Choosing separators when presenting lists of elements</li>
    <li>Controlling whether to display the question text, the answer text, or both</li>
    <li>Displaying different text depending on the value of a boolean element</li>
    <li>Displaying different text based on the sum of a 'score' value</li>
    <li>Choosing when content should appear on separate lines or the same line</li>
    <li>Combining, splitting, injecting prefixes or suffixes, or otherwise manipulating string content</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    Most importantly, all of these steps can be performed without injecting any additional items into the Questionnaire.
  </p>
  <p>
    The Liquid to be used in producing the QuestionnaireResponse narratives is placed in a Library pointed to by the <code>instance-narrative-liquid</code> extension
    appearing at the root of the Questionnare.  The Library will use the 
    <a href="https://terminology.hl7.org/en/CodeSystem-library-type.html#library-type-narrative-liquid">narrative-liquid</a> code to 
    confirm its purpose, which will be necessary if accessing the Library outside the scope of the Questionnaire.  However, this Library will generally be transmitted 
    as a 'contained' resource within the Questionnaire, ensuring it will remain available whenever the Questionnaire is accessed and helping to ensure that the Liquid 
    will be maintained as part of the Questionnaire.  When a QuestionnaireResponse is complete (or even as the QuestionnaireResponse is being authored), the Form Filler 
    can execute the Liquid against the QuestionnaireResponse, wrap the results in a <code>&lt;div/&gt;</code> element, and store the resulting HTML as the narrative 
    for the QuestionnaireResponse.  This provides an 'authoritative' human-readable view of the QuestionnaireResponse, while still allowing a rendering system to fall
    back to one of the other views if the user wishes.
  </p>
  <p>
    This approach can produce the most concise and user-friendly rendering of completed forms.  Any information about omitted answers or items that is relevant to the
    consumer can be rendered, while information not relevant can be suppressed.  The order and formatting of presentation can be completely tuned to what makes the most
    sense for a reader.  The downsides of this approach are:
  </p>
  <ol>
    <li>The form renderer must be able to process liquid or have access to a third party module that can do so</li>
    <li>The form author either needs to hand-create the Liquid to go with their form or need to embed sufficient metadata in their form to allow custom generation of the
      Liquid</li>
  </ol>
  
  <a name="liquidauthoring"> </a>
  <h5>Authoring Liquid</h5>
  <p>
    Hand authoring Liquid can be complex and potentially error prone.  If working with multiple Questionnaires, it is often more efficient to embed metadata
    within the Questionnaire and then generating the Liquid automatically.  At present, SDC does not define any 'standard' extensions to drive Liquid generation
    because the range of desired rendering behaviors is so wide.  It is possible after there is more community experience with the use of thie approach that a
    future version of this guide might choose to define standard versions of at least some Liquid-control metadata extensions.  For now, an example of a Questionnaire
    that has such custom extensionsa as well as the resulting contained Liquid library can be found <a href="Questionnaire-CardiologyForm.html">here</a>.  
    An example of a response with the narrative generated from that Liquid can be found <a href="QuestionnaireResponse-Cardiology-MariaSantos.html">here</a>.
  </p>
</div>
